Cuban Imprints Collection
Cuban Imprints Collection
1993-1994
2 folders (SC)
Five limited-edition artists' books, published by Ediciones Vigía. Printed on brown wrapping paper, printed white paper overlays, bound with string ties. Six brochures for various Cuban artists from Banco de Ideas Z., printed on brown paper.
2464625
Biographical History
Ediciones Vigía, founded in 1985, is a collective of book artists in Matanzas, Cuba which brings together poets, writers, illustrators and designers. The small group of about fifteen people uses recycled and natural materials to create handmade books. Only 200 copies of each book are made, all produced at the same time, with each binding and text element added one-by-one. Most of the books use the standard Cuban government-issued, highly acidic tan paper. Illustrations are done by hand in pen and ink and reproduced on one of the collective's few machines, a photocopier or a mimeograph machine. The artists use recycled paper and cloth, as well as natural materials such as flowers, stones, dirt and leaves to create collage images for the covers. [Information taken from Ediciones Vigía website]
Banco de Ideas Z. is a non-profit arts center in Havana, Cuba whose aim is to promote Cuban independent artists. It publishes and promotes literary text compilations and the works of authors, book-artists (both individual and collective), dramatists, theater groups and so on.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Cuban Imprints Collection consists of two series. Ediciones Vigía consists of five books published by Ediciones Vigía. Four appear to be plays; the fifth appears to be poetry. Each book is printed on rough brown or white paper with overlays of printed white paper, brown paper, and string, and bound with string ties. Illustrations are hand-colored. Banco de Ideas Z. comprises six gallery brochures or fliers, five printed on plain brown paper, the sixth on white paper, featuring various artists.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical by publisher.
Subject and Genre Headings
Publishing, printing and book arts; Art -- Illustrators; Fernández, René,1944-; Guerra, Charo, 1962-; Ruiz Montez, Laura.; Banco de Ideas Z (Havana, Cuba); Ediciones Vigía.; Los ibeyis y el diablo.; Los inocentes.; Historia de burros.; ¡tierra a la vista!; Yo amo a este hombre viejo que a ratos le falta el aire.; Art, Cuban -- 20th century.; Artists' books -- Cuba.; Artists -- Cuba.; Authors -- Cuba.; Cuban drama.; Cuban literature.; Artists' books.; Books.; Fliers (printed matter); Limited editions.; Artists.; Poets.; Authors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ted Aiken, 2006.
Inventory
- Ediciones Vigía
  - Fernández, René
    - Historia de burros, 1994 (Sc 174/1)
    - Los ibeyis y el diablo, 1993 (Sc 174/1)
    - ¡Tierra a la vista!, 1994 (Sc 174/1)
  - Guerra, Charo
    - Los inocentes, 1993 (Sc 174/1)
  - Ruiz Montez, Laura
    - Yo amo a este hombre viejo que a ratos le falta el aire, 1993 (Sc 174/1)
- Banco de Ideas Z.
  - Gallery fliers, artists represented are Enrique Lanza, Madelín Tamayo, Jose Garcia Montebravo, María de los Angeles Vidal, Osvaldo Castillo Vázquez, and Marcela Zequiera. (Sc 174/2)